This is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net.
SE radio is brought to you by the ITE computer society.
and by it e software magazine online at computer.org/software.
[music]
Hi, this is Priyanka Ravan for software engineering radio.
Today we'll be exploring the topic how to build an LLM based application, diving into the.
right use cases, architectural choices and how to select the right models for your needs.
My guest today is Shjina Meugo, a seasoned researcher having worked with research labs at Yahoo,
IBM, Google and Amazon.
with more than two decades of experience tackling largecale data science challenges across enterprises, e-commerce and government collaborations.
Shina holds a PhD in computer science from the University of Texas at Austin.
and a bachelor's in electrical engineering from the Indian Institute of Technology Midas.
Welcome to the show Sujana.
Hey Brianka, great to be here with you and thanks so much for having me on your show.
Pretty excited about this discussion and I'm looking forward to it.
Though we have done many shows on large language models such as episode 582 programming with LLMs,
episode 533 on GitHub copilot, episode 673 on.
rag, and recently episode 693 on AI assisted debugging.
it would still be beneficial for our listeners.
if you could define a few terms before we move deeper into the show.
The first one I wanted to ask is what is the difference between generative AI versus deep learning.
versus predictive AI?
Yeah, this is a great place to start.
So before we get into the deeper nuances of generative AI,
I really think we should clear up some of the vocabulary that gets tossed around.
So let's imagine a vin diagram with nested circles.
So the largest circle here would be AI.
that encompasses all kinds of intelligence that do not have a natural origin.
Historically, these used to include even rule-based expert systems.
and smart search algorithms like the ones used in earlier versions of the Stockfish chess engine.
However, the most important AI methods are the ones based on machine learning.
where we learn patterns from data.
So, ML is sort of nested inside AI though nowadays they've become nearly synonymous.
Now within machine learning the current dominant subclass of algorithms are deep learning methods.
and these are methods based on multi-layered neural networks.
and these include models such as RNN's recurrent neural networks.
and CNN's convolutional neural networks and also the most recent crop of generative AI models.
Now the generative AI models are the ones.
that ingest inputs and they generate artifacts of complex modalities like text, speech, images, video and so on.
and the ones that focus on language in particular for instance the original GPT models are called generative.
LLMs where LLM stands for large language models.
So essentially we have these concentric circles of AI.
then ML then deep learning then generative AI and within that generative LLM.
Now Priyanka you also asked me about predictive AI.
This is sometimes referred to as discriminative AI.
and these are models that output numeric scores or vectors or categorical labels.
Unlike the generative AI models that output complex artifacts like text and images,
most of the ML work till recent years used to focus on predictive and discriminative models.
and that span different model classes like decision trees, kernel machines, linear models and neural networks.
Now from an application point of view, classification of an email as spam or.
not would be something powered by predictive or discriminative methods while generating that email would require generative AI.
So I hope that clears it up.
I think it does and we can move on to the next terms I want you to define.
for me which is what is the pre-trained model versus.
when someone says you need to fine-tune a model.
Right. Right. Yeah.
So to understand these terms pre-training and finetuning let's take a step back.
and look at how generative models are trained.
Now this process is a little different from the traditional supervised learning paradigm.
where we train models on labeled examples like emails marked as spam or not.
and traditionally this learning used to be for a specific task.
Generative models on the other hand go through a multi-stage training process.
that closely mimics how humans learn and specialize.
So here the first stage which is pre-training essentially gives the model broad education about the world.
The model learns from massive amounts of unlabelled data.
that is we don't have any labels and these could be books, Wikipedia, public web and so on.
and this is done without any specific target task.
So in this phase, the model learns broad patterns.
and reasoning structures just like how people learn foundational knowledge in school.
For instance, a language model might learn grammar,
idoms and context and a vision model would learn about spatial coherence.
and patterns like humans having five fingers and not six.
And the result is a powerful foundation model.
which understands this broad domain of text.
or images and it understands it deeply enough to generate realistic continuations.
So think of this as some sort of powerful autocomplete.
Now once we are done with this pre-training stage,
the next stage is the supervised fine-tuning stage.
and this is similar to vocational training of humans for specific professions.
So here what we do is tweak the model parameters for a particular task.
or set of tasks using label data. Right?
Now LLM providers like Google or OpenA already do some fine-tuning for very common tasks like say summarization,
question answering and so on.
But in some cases, organizations might want to fine-tune pre-trained models on their proprietary data to further enhance. the performance.
So they use a variety of methods.
and these span a large spectrum from updating all of the model parameters to adjusting just a few.
using lightweight techniques like LoRa, which is low rank adaptation.
Now I want to mention that in addition to pre-training and fine-tuning that you asked about Priyanka,
there's actually an important third stage which is alignment.
So this is about guiding the model's behavior to ensure that the responses are helpful,
safe and aligned with human expectations.
So this stage is a bit like giving people performance feedback after they are on the job.
So the model is already generating responses and then we are flagging it as good or not.
And this step uses techniques like reinforcement learning from human feedback that's called RLHF and now.
there are more recent techniques like PO proximal policy optimization DPO which stands for direct preference optimization.
Well, let's not bother about the various techniques,
but the whole idea here is that the models are now trained to prefer responses.
that are better suited for human preferences.
Now, outside the ML community, folks have been using fine-tuning to refer to any form of customization,
whether that's supervised fine-tuning or alignment or even prompting it. Right?
So that kind of works informally but in technical settings it's better to use fine-tuning to refer to.
the supervised finetuning step.
It would make sense to move on to the next question.
which is also important which is the term transformers which is used in GPTs.
What does that do?
Right. Right.
Let's see the T in GPT actually stands for the transformer architecture.
and that is the core model architecture powering today's LLMs.
So this was first proposed in 2017 in the famous attention is all you need paper.
and it's designed around the idea of attention which is essentially a mechanism.
that lets the model focus on the most relevant parts of the input.
when it's trying to either create an embedding or generate predictions.
So typically in language models we encode input sentences as sequences of tokens.
Tokens are essentially parts of words and you can think of these tokens as atomic units of the. model's language.
Now in earlier language models like RNNs,
we used to process this input data step by step in a sequential manner.
But in transformers, we handle all tokens in parallel and that makes it highly flexible and scalable.
In fact, this was the innovation that made it feasible for us to build these massive models with.
billions of parameters.
Now to go a little deeper in the transformer architecture, we have two main components.
One is the encoder and the other is the decoder.
Now the encoder takes the input, our sequence of tokens.
and it processes it through layers of self attention.
That is each token gets to look at all the other tokens.
and this enables the model to understand relationships between all parts of the input.
and as a result we get a set of very rich contextual embeddings.
Embeddings are nothing other than just vectors, right?
So we have representations for each of the token in the form of a numeric vector.
and that encodes the meaning of the sentence.
So essentially we are translating the input text to a vector.
Now the decoder takes these embedding representations.
or vectors and again uses the attention mechanism to generate output text one token at a time.
Now some of the earlier models that were around like Google's T5 had both encoder and decoder.
Most of the current generative LLMs like GPT only use the decoder and it's optimized for text generation.
And of course we also have models like BERT.
which only use the encoder because it's targeted towards understanding the text doesn't have generative responsibilities.
and you know now we've gone beyond text to other modalities.
and some of these ideas are being used there as well.
Yeah. So based on what you just said.
where we go beyond the text and we use multimodal which is both images.
and videos or anything else could you talk to us about two other terms.
which is diffusion model versus vision transformers. Oh yeah. Yeah.
I mean I'm glad you brought this up.
because now we've made a lot of progress on vision models and.
most of the genet tools that we use like charge GPT actually support both vision.
and language and in fact audio too.
So while folks were exploring language focused generative models,
there was also this big parallel effort on image generation.
and this separate evolution came about because of a fundamental difference between language and image modalities.
So if you think about it, language is discrete and sequential.
So words come in a fixed order.
and that results in a distinct meaning and so predicting the next token made a lot of sense.
Images on the other hand are continuous.
and spatial and the meaning emerges from patterns across pixels rather than their order.
So transformer architectures.
which excelled at handling dependencies across a sequence of tokens were a natural fit for a language.
But for image models, we needed architectures that could deal with noise and spatial coherence.
So it turned out that diffusion models which were first studied in physics were a good fit.
So these diffusion models learn to create images using a simple but powerful idea.
And the idea is something like this.
You take real pictures, gradually add random noise until the picture becomes completely unrecognizable.
and then we train the model to reverse this process via what we call it dinoising.
So essentially we recover the original image by removing one step at a time,
one iteration at a time.
Once we train this model over millions of images,
it learns visual patterns that make an image look real like the edges,
the lighting, perspective, texture and all that.
Once we have a train model, we run this model in reverse.
So we start from random noise and.
then we do this iterative dnoising one step at a time until we have a coherent image.
Now given some input text instructions or a reference image, if you.
want to generate an image, we first encode those inputs as vectors.
and those vectors steer this image generation.
So you can think of diffusion models as digital artists.
who are splattering paint all around and then they're sculpting some order out of chaos.
So in essence the model turns that random spray of paint into realistic images one brush stroke at.
a time.
and most of the earlier versions of Dali and stable diffusion were this pure diffusion models.
So that's about the diffusion models.
Now while diffusion models were perfecting this image generation we.
also had big advances in the field of image understanding.
and that was done through vision transformers or vit.
The second class of models that you asked about.
So the core innovation in vit is that we treat an image exactly like a sentence.
So we break the image into a sequence of small patches.
or visual tokens and then we feed it into a standard transformer architecture.
The one that we talked about a little while ago.
Now this allows the model to learn not only local.
but long range dependencies across all the tokens of the image.
This was not possible with the earlier generation of vision models.
which were like focused only on the local dependencies.
So vits proved that the power of attention mechanism.
which really transformed language understanding could be equally transformative for vision.
and soon it became the most dominant choice for visual understanding.
Now given that we have these tools for generation.
and understanding the obvious next step was to merge these two and that led to diffusion transformers.
So we had diffusion and we have transformers it's called DITS.
and these models essentially take the vit architecture.
and use that to replace the traditional backbone used in denoising in the diffusion model.
So we kind of like merge these two.
and this fusion is really the bedrock of our modern highly scalable.
and realistic video generation systems like open AI sura.
So we have now all of these cool models and we have both the vision.
and language merged in unified models as well because we have transformers and diffusion models combined.
Wow, this is fascinating and it would make sense to go to the next part now.
that we've got the definitions out of the way.
We have discussed use cases in other episodes which we did on large language models,
but it was mainly to do with code generation and debugging and programming.
But this area is also transforming areas like video creation like you just alluded to text editing.
and even medical sciences.
From your experience, what are common use cases where Genai is used?
Yeah.
And it's really true that there's so many use cases right now.
And it's pretty remarkable how things are shaping up.
and it's really become a very versatile engine that's reshaping a lot of domains.
And if you look at the landscape today,
I would group the most impactful gener use cases into four main buckets.
The first one is really where it started for most of us.
and that is chat bots or software knowledge copilots like chat GPT Gemini claude.
and these are systems designed to augment human intelligence and productivity.
What makes them so powerful is their dual capability.
On one hand, these co-pilots interact with humans in our natural modalities like text,
audio, images or even video.
and on the other hand they can also talk to automated tools through API calls.
So this bridging capability is a gamecher.
On top of that the underlying models also come with world knowledge.
They're getting progressively better at reasoning, planning, and they can tap into internet resources when needed.
As we all know, for the software engineering community,
this shift has been transformative given how quickly people have adopted all of these codecentric gen.
tools like GitHub, Copilot, and Cursor AI.
Most of you I'm sure are already using these tools for code refactoring,
debugging, for unit test, design documents and so on.
It's the same story in all knowledge inensive domains.
So I don't have to go into details there.
In fact, I would say that for most knowledge workers,
tools like Microsoft Copilot have become the ultimate personal assistants.
because they handle everything from meeting summaries, email drafts and even creating complex reports.
So that's the first big bucket.
Now the second class of use cases revolves around process automation and agentic systems.
Now unlike co-pilots where we still have a human in the loop,
these are autonomous agents and they can plan and execute multi-step tasks on their own.
So typically these agents would handle workflows that would normally be assigned to a human,
something like auditing suspicious e-commerce transactions, planning travel, doing some analysis of stocks.
And increasingly we are seeing customized task specific agents being built for various domains on top of frameworks.
like open AI assistant API autogrew AI.
Now apart from these first two buckets there is a very important third bucket.
that most of us seem to be encountering which is multimodel content design and creation.
And this is the creative frontier of Gen AI.
As we just now discussed, we have these powerful diffusion transformer and neural radiance based models.
And these include the latest versions of Dali, VO and Tream Fusion.
Tam Fusion is the one for generating 3D scenes.
And these models can generate highly realistic output images,
video, 3D models from text or even other reference input.
And they can do this with high fidelity and coherent style.
And the same is now true for audio models which can be used to generate music, human speech,
and even environmental sounds.
And as a result of all of this,
we are seeing a dramatic overhauling of content creation workflows across advertising, across film making, game design,
architecture design and a lot of other domains.
Now apart from these three buckets that we might have encountered in our everyday lives,
there is an important fourth bucket.
which is actually the most profound one and that is scientific discovery.
If you saw last year's Nobel Prize awards, you would definitely relate to this.
So here genai is acting as an instrument of science in various application domains.
and one important use case is custom models to generate new structured artifacts.
For instance, models like alpha fold 3 are helping design entirely new protein structures and molecules.
which is accelerating drug discovery in ways that used to be unthinkable a few years ago.
Apart from this, another critical work stream is generation of synthetic data sets that mimic real data and.
that's particularly important for high stakes domains like healthcare and finance where privacy and safety are very important.
So just to sum up Priyanka, the use cases seeing rapid adoption are the ones.
that involve high volume knowledge synthesis.
or complex creative generation or foundational discovery.
where the alternative would have been very time consuming and an expensive human process.
Okay, that's great.
And since we are doing a show on how to build an LLM based application,
where does it not make sense to use an LLM?
Yeah.
Now given all the hype around generative AI,
right, it's really really important to have a decision framework for building a gen application.
And there really are three big questions here.
The first is the one that you asked, is it going to help or not?
Right? So we need to sort that out.
and the second one is what's the right solution approach and the third one is around model choices.
but the very first one is the most important and critical one.
Now to understand why LLMs might not be the optimal choice for some applications we need to first.
consider the relative strengths and weaknesses of these genai models.
So if you think about it these models come with built-in world knowledge.
They offer very powerful understanding and generation capabilities across unstructured modalities like text images.
and the downside though is that they can result in high latency.
and computation cost and often they can hallucinate or lead to safety risks.
So for any application we need to really evaluate what these models offer relative to the current baselines.
Now the benefits could be in the form of the improved time to solve,
improved quality, a reduction in cost or new capabilities that were not possible before.
Now this evaluation is critical because if we don't do it, we might end up with poor choices.
Now broadly speaking, there are three groups of applications.
where gen models turn out to be a poor fit when we do this evaluation of benefits.
And let me call out these three groups.
The first one is applications that do not involve understanding.
or generation over unstructured input like text and images.
And obviously because the models forte is this unstructured input.
So if we are not dealing with it maybe we don't need them as much.
And examples here include inventory optimization or structured predictive analytics based on tabular numeric data.
Now the second group includes high stakes applications.
which are centered around understanding but not generation of unstructured inputs and this could be like fraud detection,
medical diagnosis.
Here we are still dealing with unstructured inputs.
but we are only understanding and the accuracy bar is really high.
and usually for such task we also have a lot of task specific label data.
So it's better to train highly accurate.
and controllable encoder models that can be efficiently retrained as new data keeps coming in than go to.
generative models.
Now the third group includes realtime high volume low latency systems like transaction scoring.
or e-commerce product search ranking.
where the computational cost and the inherent latency of generative models just makes them impractical for production use.
Yeah, I mean now of course I can go into more detail.
but these are the three broad buckets.
If I were to summarize this, if you needed an application with a lot of accuracy.
and it has already been worked on with pre-existing modeling.
and an solution exists, then don't go.
and use generative AI in these cases cuz it would not make sense.
and also the fact that you might have some latency requirements that have to be met.
which your current app does then do not move to creating an LLM based app.
Absolutely. Yeah.
Let's move on to the next part of the show.
which is we're going to talk about how we are going to choose a right.
model to build an LLM based application.
And for this I wanted to ask you the how based on an illustrative application.
Suppose I'm building an e-commerce app to buy tennis rackets.
and the goal is to connect tennis buyers with the products they love be it a racket.
or an accessory. How could a gen AI based app help here?
Oh yeah that's a great example.
So when we are building an app say in this case to connect tennis buyers to products.
or for.
that matter any rich app it's almost never a single task like I mentioned the product search ranking.
it's not like that.
in reality we'll need multiple capabilities and the gen solve for each of these capabilities could be slightly.
different.
so let me clarify that with the example.
so here let's step back and think what needs to be built for this particular scenario.
Essentially, we want to replicate a tennis store salesperson with this application.
So, if we were to walk into a sports store to buy a new racket or shoes,
the salesperson doesn't just, you know, give us a product.
They start by understanding our needs.
So, first, just by looking at us,
they might make some implicit inferences about gender, whether we are left or right-handed.
and then they might ask some questions like what are we using,
what issues do we have and even probably see a short video of the swing.
So this first step is all about eliciting and understanding requirements.
So what we need here is a multimodal conversational interaction that allows text, image and video inputs. Huh?
So here beyond the plain knowledge that we might have like plain world knowledge, we might.
also need some tennis expertise to understand what the customer is really saying.
and also ask the right questions to drill down.
Now once we are done with this stage,
the salesperson would mentally shortlist a few products and come back to the customer. Right?
That is the retrieval stage.
So in the digital version, the app needs to do this at a large scale,
matching thousands of products to the users's needs.
And often there's a vocabulary gap between the user language.
The user might say a beginner racket.
and the product spec might have something else like a graphite frame.
and we need to bridge this gap.
Now this requires deep domain expertise on which products match which user profile.
A salesperson would have built up this expertise over years.
But in case of the application, we'll need to leverage historical transactions and customers behavioral data.
Say what similar buyers have preferred in the past, right?
And the way we do this is represent the customer's needs.
and the product specs in a shared semantic space and then we do the matching.
Now once we have done this retrieval the user might have questions about the products.
that we are recommending maybe the top three products we are recommending.
they might want to know about discounts.
or their relative lengths or something like.
that and that requires knowledge intensive generation because we have to be really factual.
We have to ground the responses in some real time data like the prices and discounts.
So accuracy is paramount at this stage.
Now in addition to answering the customer's questions, we also need to present it properly.
So the shopper might want to visualize the racket or in case it's shoes,
they might want to try that on.
And there we might need some sort of multimodel generation capabilities like say virtual tryon.
And it's not just the visual presentation even the tone and language matter.
So we might want to use the language that a salespersons would like say.
that this is an excellent choice or this fits your play style because that really boosts the conversion.
And this part is less about the knowledge aspect but more about just creating friendly emotionally intelligent language.
And just to summarize right so the first stage was understanding the requirements again in a multimodal fashion.
Then there was retrieval.
Then there was knowledge intensive generation and maybe reasoning.
And then there was the presentation which again could be multimodel and also involve persuasive language.
So these are all the different capabilities.
and I wanted to call these out separately.
because the gen solve for each of these could be different. Yeah.
So once we know that these are the buckets then we can drill down.
and typically what we need to do is break down the application into components.
or capabilities and then solve for each.
because the baseline might be different for each.
and you know the choices that you have in terms of models might be different for each.
So you will benefit from having a modular solution.
Great.
So these four big buckets have to be understood by anyone trying to build an LLM based application. which will.
then mean that you would get better results cuz you're making sure.
that these four buckets are taken care of.
I think it's fascinating really good.
I would have to go on to the next question.
But before that I should tell you the presentation is a very important aspect as you said because.
recently two weeks back I burnt about equivalent to $100 in Indian rupees because someone told me.
that the tennis shoe that I was buying would make me play like Roger Fedra.
[laughter]
So yeah. Yeah. It's a very similar thing. A good app.
I mean from their perspective I think that was a good sale.
Of course, not necessarily the right thing maybe for the customer but yes that is great.
So I think it would make sense to move on to the next question.
which is I would like to know.
what kind of model metrics do I need to be aware of up front to understand.
if my application is working correctly.
Okay.
So Priyanka, I was just wondering, would you like me to drill down into the solve for each.
of these before getting into the model metric?
Yeah. Yeah, that'll be good. Let me do that and then I think when we get to the metrics,
it'll be like sort of clear.
because I just called out the various capabilities or the classes of capabilities.
The thing to remember is like I said earlier the solve for each is different.
and it really depends on what you care about right for your particular application.
and the factors that you need to consider are how quickly do you need the solution how accurate.
you need to be how much label data you have.
whether you have the capacity to build ML models in terms of the team and the compute infra.
and there are all these other considerations on the application settings like latency and throughput requirements.
Is the content directly going to be sent to the users.
or is it an offline process that where content sensitivity risks are lowered.
So these are considerations one needs to factor in.
and based on that you have a different solve for each of these capabilities.
And let me go over the four different task buckets I called out right which.
were there's understanding and then there's retrieval both of which are discriminative and then there is generation.
So in generation we have knowledge intensive generation.
and then there is generation which is based on wool knowledge.
Now I'm like setting aside the multimodality.
because the multimodality is an aspect that cuts through all of these four buckets.
It's like applicable to all of them.
So coming to understanding this task is about interpreting unstructured inputs.
We are not doing any generation and this includes task like classification,
entity recognition, object detection, segmentation and so on.
And here the output comes from some welldefined close set.
And in this case, if your accuracy bar is on the lower side,
you can quickly get good results by doing some smart prompting of foundation models.
So even though it's understanding, you can use a generative model.
Say you're doing a text classification, you can use a generative model.
If your accuracy bar is not so high,
if the accuracy bar is high and you have lots of label data.
and you are well equipped to train ML models, then it's a good idea to fine-tune encoder models.
Though here you're not going to benefit from fine-tuning generative models.
because that's expensive and you can't repeat it frequently.
Encoder model is a right choice and it'll also be efficient.
The next category that I mentioned is retrieval.
Again, this is a discriminative task.
And here we typically have a query and a repository of artifacts like products, images and so on.
And usually you have to rank these artifacts based on the match score.
Now when the scale is small, it's almost like understanding.
But when the scale is large, then you can't use a very simple prompting based solution at all.
Because if I have let's say in this case that you mentioned Priyanka with the tennis products.
if I have say 100,000 tennis products there is no way I can fit in the description of.
all of those products in the prompt of a generative model.
So even when we want to do a prompting based solution,
we start with some simple solution like say.
if you were to use elastic search you'll have term frequency inverse document frequency TF. or BM25 based retrieval.
You use that and then find a small set of matches.
and then you take those and feed that into your generative model and get the top ones.
So you essentially rerank them.
That would be the first cut.
solution when you don't have lot of label data.
and no ML capacity and accuracy is not such a big deal.
but for this retrieval problem if accuracy is important and you do have label data then.
again the best thing to do is to go back to encoder models.
and really train them and then use that to find the best matching products.
Now there's a small subset of cases.
where generative AI models are useful and that is the cases where we have a cold start situation.
where we don't have label data for some queries.
or for some new artifacts that have been added to our repository.
For such cases, generative AI model helps.
But typically the way we use it is we use them to generate synthetic data offline and.
then we use that synthetic data along with the other label data to train the encoder models.
So again here we have a simple first cut solution and then a complex one.
The simple first cut solution uses a weak retrieval.
and then a generative prompting base layer on top of that.
The complex one just trains encoder models and then does matching.
Yeah.
So this was for the first two buckets.
Now the third one is generation where we only need world knowledge and tasks like summarization,
persuasive copywriting or some simple image edits would fall into this category.
Now most foundation models are trained very well.
So the simplest and often the most effective thing to do is just smart prompting with these foundation. models.
And if we really want to optimize for latency,
that is the only case when we want might choose to fine-tune our own custom models.
Now the fourth bucket that I called out was the knowledge intensive generation.
And here we need uh deep domain knowledge.
because we need to ground this in facts and up-to-date information.
And for this case the foundation models won't work well.
because they might hallucinate or they might respond with outdated info.
So the first cut solution itself is drag or retrieval augmented generation.
So here the system would retrieve some relevant information from a database and then you know.
feed just that relevant bit of information to the generative model which will generate the final response.
and again you know as you get more propriety data you know you can.
and you have more capacity to fine-tune models one can choose to fine-tune domain specific solution.
So just to summarize for each of these four categories right we do have a simple solution.
which would involve prompting a generative model.
but for the special buckets that we called out like retrieval.
and knowledge intensive generation we need to actually augment that generation with some retrieval.
and the complex path is of course to fine-tune our custom models.
which could be encoder based models models.
for the first two buckets and it would be generative models for the second two ones.
So I just wanted to mention this because you know people almost always just rush to generative models.
but that's not necessarily the right solve most of the time because it will not be accurate.
It might not be accurate.
It might be more intensive and it like ties back to your question Priyankon.
when it would not be optimal. Right?
So these are like the variations of how we do the solve.
So now should we go on to the metrics that we-
Oh yeah defin definitely so let me come back to the question on metrics right.
so like I called out so.
we had to figure out whether it was good.
or not like LLMs or generative models in general are good or not.
then the solve depending on the capability and then we have to decide the right model.
and to do that the first thing you have to do is pick a set of candidate models.
that you really need to compare.
and for that you need to very clear on the input and output modalities of the task.
So what are we giving to the model and what do we want it to generate like you.
know is text to text or is this text plus images resulting in an image and so on.
Sometimes we might even have some specialized variations like code gene sequence models.
and we need to make sure that the candidate pool includes models for that specialized variants.
and also the generalpurpose copilots like charg.
because these generalpurpose copilots now invoke specialized models under the hood.
Now once we have this set of candidate models there are two broad sets of considerations.
The first set is qualitative factors and you should examine this up front.
because that will narrow the choices and it's like lower effort in general.
and then come the quantitative one which we validate through rigorous experiments.
So the qualitative ones mostly deal with governance, legal and operational factors.
and these include deciding whether we want open access models where we can see and.
fine-tune the parameters or closed ones like GPT where we can only access through an API.
So nowadays some of the closed one or the blackbox models do allow us to fine-tune but.
that would require like sharing your own data on the cloud and that might not be feasible.
So this is an important consideration.
Another consideration is whether the usage license fits the need.
I mean is sometimes we might just be looking to experiment.
or do research but if it's a commercial product then we need to be careful about this aspect.
We also need to evaluate the liabilities for copyright infringement.
and whether our particular usage scenario is approved or.
not like say retraining with the model output.
because that's not permitted by a lot of models like chart GPT and claude.
Now in addition to these constraints, we.
also need to look at computation cost and throughput limits to see if they fit the application needs.
because there might be an application latency and there might be an application budget.
So these are all like things that we can do up front.
Now when it comes to the qualitative a quantitative evaluation you know.
before we go to doing something specific on our own data it's always a good idea to look.
at public leader boards maintained by hugging.
phase artificial analysis AI LMA and so on.
and look at the relevant benchmark so that we can narrow the candidate list because.
any experimentation is going to be costly.
because we like literally paying money for every invocation of these models, right?
So, you want to narrow down the list.
Now, within the quantitative metrics, the most important ones are the ones that pertain to response quality.
And these vary again based on the tasks or the capabilities that we talked about.
In case of understanding or retrieval, we might track precision, recall or ranking metrics.
In case of just world knowledge based generation,
we might look at fluency, realism of the images or alignment with the instructions.
In case of knowledge intensive generation, we would look at the regret rate,
what fraction of questions it's unable to answer.
We might also look at factual accuracy, completeness of the response and so on.
Now for heavily regulated domains like healthcare you know legal advice in addition to these generic typical ML.
metrics we should also look at metrics around out of scope detection.
So we should not be answering things which are not within the scope of application.
Right?
So for that we need to detect it ahead of time.
You know whether we are leaking confidential data or PI data that's an important metric.
Safety of the content compliance with guidelines.
All of these need to be measured quantitatively on data sets and this would ensure that.
you know the model not only performs well but actually behaves responsibily for our scope and context.
Now in addition to the response quality we.
also need to assess the average latency the average input context length.
and output response length for our particular use case.
And that's important because we need to be able to understand the costbenefit tradeoffs of all the models. that we are evaluating.
I just want to step back and say.
that you know this quantitative evaluation with representative unseen test data sets and welldefined metrics.
This is the core pillar of ML modeling. Yeah.
Right now I see a lot of folks.
who skip this step or do it in an ad hoc fashion and.
it then comes back to bite you later.
because things won't work in production if you haven't done the proper evaluation.
and in fact I would say even before we build out a solution.
It's always nice to lay down that success criteria in terms of hard metrics.
actually derived from the business needs.
and representative data sets that you know mimic the production setting.
and we need to implement an automated evaluation mechanism.
So in the beginning the data sets might be very small the metrics might not be complete that's. all fine.
but as long as you set this up and you automate it it'll make sure that.
you will keep doing this evaluation and whenever there's a regression you'll be able to track it.
So what's happening right now is you know the gen models are.
actually evolving way more rapidly than our application needs.
So new models are being released every.
so often and if we have this evaluation framework set up then as soon.
as a new model comes in you can easily plug it in compute the metrics.
and you know swap out the models as required.
So that's the right way to do you know this application building.
I think that's a very good point that you brought out because if you.
set the ground success criteria that will help you in also changing models as they keep appearing.
Yeah, I think that's a very good rule of thumb I think that we should follow.
Now like to move into the LLM application architecture under the hood.
The reason I want to talk about it is.
because we've fairly run out of time talking a lot about the model.
I want to briefly ask you to lay down what are the typical components.
that one sees on LLM based applications mainly looking at the architecture over here.
and can you also tell me which is the most important part if that's possible-
got it yeah so far we were like talking about metrics.
and the solution from an ML perspective right.
but when we really design these systems you need to think about the software architecture ure of LLM. applications.
and the thing that's like working for a lot of people.
when it comes to building real large scale applications is this agentic approach.
and most of the applications we build typically will not you know be the.
right fit for one big monolithic model.
you know because you can't just have one model serving your text.
and images so it you can't control it as efficiently.
so when you craft it well.
It is a modular agentic system with multiple components and together they take care of planning,
execution, memory, reasoning, actions and even reflection and learning over time.
So to understand what's going on, imagine a well-run project team.
where each component maps to a specific role.
So at the top we have the planner.
or the project head and this is the person who understands the overall requirements.
and translates those requirements into a structured plan breaking the work down into smaller actionable tasks.
that the rest of the team can execute.
Note that the planner doesn't actually do the work.
The planner only defines what needs to be done and in what order.
Now this is where the orchestrator steps in.
So the orchestrator is like the program manager, the one who ensures.
that the plan actually gets executed by coordinating between the various members of the team.
or in our case the other components of the system.
So this orchestrator is not just a messenger keeps an eye on the progress and.
if something goes wrong can go back to the planner and you know re-trigger the replanning.
So together the planner and orchestrator form the control loop of the system.
So the planner designs the road map and the orchestrator ensures that the journey stays on track.
Now supporting these two is memory.
Think of this as you know the project archive assistant who's responsible.
for maintaining the meeting note all the decisions task updates.
so that the everybody in the team has the right context.
Now without memory the system might forget the context or repeat unnecessary work or repeat errors.
But with memory the agent can reason pretty coherently across sessions.
or in case of chat you know across various turns of conversation.
Now at the core of all of this planning.
and orchestration memory we actually have something even more important which is the LLM itself.
Think of this as the expert strategist or like the Yoda of the team.
This is the systems reasoning and thinking engine and this is the one that interprets the goals,
reflects on the past outcomes and it provides intelligent guidance.
So this module doesn't actually execute anything.
but it's the central intelligence that everyone else depends on the for guidance.
So this works behind the scene.
Now apart from all of these four core components, we also have a tool layer which.
typically varies from application to application and these are like the specialist members of the team.
So the tools could be something like the programmers or the graphic designers,
business analysts and they do specific jobs which is assigned to them by the orchestrator.
Now in an automated system these tools are APIs.
or external models or any kind of task specific components.
Yeah, there are few special kinds of tools that are worth mentioning.
The first one is a retriever tool.
Sometimes people refer to it as a knowledge access tool.
and this is equivalent to a research analyst who goes and fetches information. Right?
We already saw that retrieval augmented generation that's RAD.
There is a specialized retriever tool that goes and fetches information from databases or some external repositories.
and that enables the agent to have access to factual information and you know grounds it.
The second one which is again very important is a safety or guardrails tools.
Sometimes this is actually implemented across different layers as separate tools.
but essentially it plays a role of a compliance or you know quality assurance officer.
Uh it makes sure that the input is within scope.
and the output is safe and aligned to the policy guidelines.
Right? So that is the job of this tool.
Now just wanted to call out that you know these tools don't just handle information they can even.
perform actions like uh a tool could go and.
fill a form just like a human would do send emails you know control a mouse.
or in case of embodied systems it can capture images stuff like that.
So putting it all together, the planner decides what needs to happen.
The orchestrator manages how it happens.
The LLM provides the intelligence.
Memory ensures that there is continuity of the context and the tools do all the specialized work.
And you know this process is also iterative. It's not like a linear flow.
And you know planning, execution, reflection, learning, all of this happens in loops.
Mhm.
And there was this question that you had Priyanka on.
which is the most important would say the planner orchestrator combination is really the control loop.
and then of course the LLM itself.
because that is really the intelligence that powers it all right.
and the tools give you the specific things that you require.
So in our tennis case that we discussed earlier,
you would have a specialist tool to give uhme level recommendations that would be implemented in this tools,
right? Absolutely.
So you might have a retrieval tool,
you might have a specialized virtual tryon tool which is the one that sold you Roger Fred shoes.
So you might have some things like that that are invoked by the orchestrator depending on the need.
I think this has been great because I think we've got a good overview of the architecture.
The question I wanted to ask logically next would be when you work with an LLM based app.
as um developers or software engineers outside sometimes we interact with one monolith it's a black box.
You just send a prompt and you get back return.
And then sometimes as you say you add a rag and then sometimes there's this agentic AI architecture.
where there's a master agent and a lot of I know slave agents if which do the job.
Could you talk a little bit about that?
How does that fit into the architecture you just now talked about?
Right. Right.
And I'm glad you asked this because you know I don't want folks to think.
that rag architecture is something different from any of these right from the agentic one.
that we just talked about.
So what's happening here is if you look at a monolithic model it is a team with one. player.
That one player is doing everything right is doing the planning orchestration the LLM response. and there's no need for tools.
So that's what's happening in case of a monolithic model.
In case of rag, you just have a very lean team with essentially three players.
So because there is a single flow, there is no need for a plan or a planner.
So we don't need a planner there.
And what we have there is one tool.
which is a retriever which is going and fetching the relevant information.
we have an extremely simplified orchestrator which is just a messenger boy taking the retrieved information to the.
LLM which is generating the response.
So it is kind of like a simplified version of this architecture.
which might make sense for some applications.
I mean if the application is simple enough.
that every invocation only requires a retrieval operation followed by generation all you need is simple rag system.
But if you need something uh more complex where depending on the user input or depending on you.
know the nature of the application we need to make a dynamic plan then you need a planner.
and if you need a lot of different tools like sometimes you want to answer a knowledge intensive. question sometimes you.
want to solve a math problem sometimes you want to generate an image.
then you would need a whole variety of tools.
and all of this additional coordination effort does answer the query you had.
I think it does. Yeah.
So, thank you for that.
And I also wanted to ask about validation.
because often times we would like the LLM system to behave properly and avoid offensive responses,
copyright infringement, making things up.
So, how important is validation in this architecture?
Is that something that is going to be carried out by one of these specialist tools.
or do we need to do something about that outside of the LLM based application?
right and validation is definitely very very important.
because these gen systems are stochastic and unpredictable so we really need a multi-layered defense.
and like I called out there would be some of these safety tools right safety.
or compliance tool and these are actually spread across different layers.
So first you start with input validation right.
so this layer ensures that the user query or the context stays within the scope of the system.
So if it was you know an app for recommending tennis products it should not be doing any. medical diagnosis even.
if somebody were to ask a question that's not its job.
So the input layer needs to flag anything that is out of scope, unsafe, malicious upfront.
and typically we use a mix of deterministic filters like whitelisted phrases,
blacklisted phrases, reax patterns and so on and also some lightweight ML models.
lightweight because we don't want to add to the latency of generation.
and also because they are more accurate at like flagging anything that is unsafe.
and these checks have to be fast right so that's the reason we do this.
and apart from the input layer we also have some safeguards in the prompting layer.
so you can do that by giving instructions to the planner or the LLM core itself.
and not just give instructions we might.
also require require it to sort of give feedback in the form of its own confidence.
Apart from the main response, it can.
also give an output field which conveys how confident it is in this response.
which can be a signal to the orchestrator.
and the orchestrator can use that to decide.
if there's something else that needs to be done maybe another round of verification.
or just blocking the response.
Now the next layer that comes into play is the output validation.
So in the output validation layer again we have similar to the input validation we have a deterministic.
sub layer as well as a modeling based one.
The deterministic one will have blacklisted phrases and so on.
And the ML model layer could check for like things like bias,
toxicity, factual accuracy, whether it's really entailed and grounded in evidence and so on.
Now in addition to these input validation, prompting and output validation layers often we.
also have a human in the loop mechanisms like allowing the users to report problems with the output.
and also a continual audit mechanism where you know regardless of what's going on there is a sample.
being directed to human auditors to review right.
and typically the nowadays the audit systems.
and workflows are also being semi-automated by having LLMs assist the human auditors.
So just to recap, you have all of these different layers, right?
The input validation, prompting, output validation, and post response human in the loop systems.
Maybe there's a tiny thing I want to mention that in case people are wondering,
do we still need deterministic layers in this validation?
we do need it because those are the fastest ones to modify just in case something breaks right.
The quickest fix that you can do is go.
and you know add a reg pattern or like some blacklisted phrases and.
that will stop it from going viral.
and causing a lot of damage and before we can you know retrain the models.
So do a lot of the validations also outside before you send it to the model.
Yes, definitely. The next question to kind of wrap up this architecture section is to do with prompting.
All of us have read about different prompting techniques like zeroshot prompting,
few short, chain of thought, prompt chaining, chain of verification.
including reading some tips about how we should keep the prompts designed in such a way.
that the most important part of the prompts are.
either in the beginning of the prompt or the end of the prompt.
What is your take on this whole prompting and is there something that we can do?
Any tips that you can give us as listeners writing prompts?
Right. Right. Yeah.
You know the point that you mentioned on the placement is like really valid, right?
There is a lot of research on positional placement and so on.
And the key thing to remember is when we are trying to prompt,
it's almost like you're giving instructions to a human, right?
So it's important to make sure that the prompt is clear,
well structured and you know the more context and precision we give, the better the prompt performs, right?
And typically a good prompt will have elements like you know the context so that it can extrapolate.
if it needs to clear input output formats instructions.
which break down the task into simpler steps input data and examples.
So these used to be the elements of a good prompt.
Now what has happened uh lately is that the models have gotten so good.
that we don't need to do all the hard work like it is trying to figure out.
so it internally there are mechanisms to take even not.
so great prompts and rewrite them before the model actually works on it.
So that's happening with the current generation of models.
So you know the onus on us has become a little like lower than before.
You mentioned a bunch of these different techniques for prompting.
So if you think about it prompting really is like our language to talk to LLMs.
So it's essentially programming through natural language.
And most of what you called out they can just briefly go over those prompting techniques like zeroshot.
prompting is just a direct instruction.
Few short prompting is one where you give some examples.
It's also called in context learning.
So this is a case where we show a few examples.
and say you know this is how I would like you to do the job.
And for more complex reasoning we use techniques like chain of thought prompting.
and where we tell the model to think step by step and we provide examples.
So this is similar to how one might do math problems.
we would do step by step and that reduces chance of error.
Now apart from that there are lot of other variants like self-consistency, tree of thought, graph of thought.
and here the model explores multiple reasoning paths and it compares and picks the best one.
Chain of verification is another useful one.
where the prompt instructs the model to generate an answer and then double checks and critics it.
And when the tasks are you know a little bit more complex we often end up hitting context.
window limits.
So in those cases we actually break it down into multiple parts and use something called prompt chaining.
So essentially the output of one of the earlier prompts will be fed as the input to one.
of the later prompts.
So if you think of all of these techniques whether it is chain of thought,
chain of verification, prompt chaining.
or prompt decomposition, these are all very intuitive because that is how we typically solve problems as humans.
Now what I mentioned earlier, the earlier generation of these models,
we really had to be very careful in terms of how we communicate with.
these models mean how we prompt them.
But now it's become much more easy and the primary reason like called out a little.
while back is that you know a lot of these techniques have been incorporated into these models.
and the focus actually has shifted towards automated prompt optimization.
So automated prompt optimization essentially refers to methods that do away with the manual tweaking of prompts.
See in earlier days people used to train models you know with labeled examples.
So we would have like let's take a simple classification model.
We would give a labeled examples and.
then the model would look at the examples and learn the parameters.
Now what's happening with this foundation models is.
that they've kind of become like a black box to us.
and the only thing that we can tweak is the prompt.
So prompt has essentially become our parameter.
and what folks have figured out is a way to automatically tweak the prompts based on a set.
of input and output examples.
and you know some of you might know about gradient descent right.
So gradient descent is a learning algorithm.
where we you know take the old parameters we look at the loss function on our label data.
and based on that we update the parameters to give a new set.
So similar to that we now have techniques.
which are based on text gradients where we look at the old prompt. We look at the you know loss.
or some metric on a given set of labeled examples and then.
we update this prompt just said all of this is happening in the language space.
and then we get a new prompt.
Now there are a bunch of tools out there.
I particular want to call out this framework called DSPY.
and there's a nice software not just like a package but also a community around this.
So DSPY stands for declarative self-improving language programs.
and here you can declare how you want your system to be.
and it's not just a one model but it could be a fairly complex agentic system.
I mean it could be even be a simple one but it could also be a complex one.
You can just declare the architecture of your system.
and then it automatically writes the low-level prompts.
and also optimizes them once you give it a bunch of label data.
There's actually a lot of research going on in this space.
but maybe we can get to it later if we have time. Yeah.
Yeah.
Probably have another show but I will add the link to the GitHub repo which is github.comnlpy.
I think it's a great tool and you know personally I've seen great results so worth exploring.
We'll now move on to the last portion of the podcast.
Well I want to ask something about open challenges in the research area.
I have read that in the future we would have multi-ensory models.
Currently we have our voice assisted apps like Alexa.
but can you talk about any innovations that happen for the other sensory modes like smell or taste?
Yeah, you're right that we already have so many of these models that handle audio and visual inputs,
but there is uh definitely a lot of fascinating progress happening in the space of multiensory models.
and these integrate more of our human senses and I would say even go beyond them.
Meta's image bind is a prime example.
Here they have a unified representation across six different data modalities.
So that would be text, images and video,
audio, touch and force, 3D depth and even infrared thermal signals.
and these are particularly useful for robotics and embodied AI systems.
There are also breakthroughs in artificial smell.
So researchers call these electronic noses and these systems use chemical sensors to detect organic compounds in the. air.
and they can pick up a lot of things that would be completely obvious for us.
right from detecting gas leaks, monitoring air quality to analyzing human breath for signs of disease.
So there's a lot that can be done and these are quite powerful.
I want to also mention something interesting.
There is this notion of internet of senses.
You know iOS but a different iOS.
And here the idea is that the AI model can serve as a cognitive hub.
or an artificial brain that can connect and.
interpret all of these sensory inputs visual audio allactory haptic.
and so on and build a deep contextual understanding of the physical world.
For instance, if you think of what we understand as an apple, it is, you know,
the visual input, how it looks, how it smells, the touch, all of that contribute to it.
And what people are trying to do is,
you know, capture these signals through various sensors and reconstruct that conceptualization.
Now, that is the understanding part.
Now the next step is to go beyond understanding and recreate an artificial apple or.
the sensation of an apple right for somebody else.
and that's likely to lead to really rich immersive multi-ensory experiences.
Now, one other thing to remember here is that as these AI systems begin to integrate sensors.
which will capture signals across the sound and electromagnetic spectrum beyond the visible audible range, right?
It will gain the ability to sense things that we can't like, you know, things.
that are invisible, inaudible to us, things we might not be able to smell or taste.
And that opens up extraordinary possibilities which is to some extent scary.
because they will be able to perceive the world at a level much beyond our own capacities.
Pretty scary.
And I think that's something that we all have to watch out for of what the world brings.
to us with all this innovation.
I want to end the show by asking you a question.
Every day there seems to be a new innovation, a newer way of doing things.
So how to keep up with this fast pace of innovation?
Oh yeah, that's so pertinent and honestly it is difficult for all of us and you know.
I I do find the pace of innovation very dizzying.
because there's just so much happening with new tools, new models, new papers.
It literally feels like you are at the receiving end of a fire hose.
So I have my coping mechanisms and I'm sure everybody does.
So I could definitely share these.
First thing I feel is we need to make peace with the fact.
that the old education paradigm where.
we study for a few years you know school.
and college and then coast through the rest of our career.
So that one is gone.
So we definitely have to be lifelong learners.
and at the same time we also need to accept.
that we cannot stay on top of everything and you know.
because the and the other thing is it might not be important to do.
that the halflife of knowledge has become so short.
that there actually is no point learning a lot of things.
that we are not going to use right away because it's anyway going to change.
So what seems to matter a lot more now is figuring out how to learn and adapt.
And if you just look online, there's a lot of noise and very little good signal.
And so it's important for us to focus on number one,
what do we really want to acquire in terms of knowledge, right?
So it helps to curate some trustworthy sources could be newsletters could be people authoritative people.
that you follow or some forums that you participate in.
So curation of sources is important.
The second one is having a mechanism to sample what's going on.
and this could be you know a periodic activity.
In my case, just a few minutes a day, I just look through TLDDR and.
some LinkedIn posts and that gives me a sense of what new things are coming up.
And even if I don't have the bandwidth to really deep dive there,
I just kind of like bookmark it.
for later and maybe once a week I go back to look at some of the interesting things.
Now apart from this I do deep dive into topics.
that I'm really curious about or I'm going to work on soon.
And one more thing that's important is there's a lot out there that's not being peer reviewed.
So we really have to be critical in how we assess the information that's coming to us.
You know there might be great ideas there might be.
also flawed ideas and it's important us to for us to have our thinking caps on in terms. of tooling.
Priyanka I feel like tools like notion notebook llm they are pretty good.
So those are things that we could use.
I think that's a good thing that you've given us in terms of what we could look at.
things a bit more critically and curate your knowledge sources.
Thank you for coming on this show and giving us great insights.
Thanks so much Priyanka.
It was really nice chatting with you and enjoyed the discussion.
Where can people find you on cyerspace?
Just sjina@gmail.com.
That's my email.
I'll add that to the show notes. Thank you once again.
Thanks Priyanka.
This is Priyanka Raguan for software engineering radio.
Thank you for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an educational program brought to you by it e software magazine.
For more about the podcast, including other episodes, visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn,
Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack channel at seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at teamseradio.net.
[music]
This and all other episodes of SE Radio is licensed under Creative Common License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.